<!-- Rachel -->
<?xml-model href="magellan.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<magellan type="navigationTreatise">
    <header>
        <title>TREATISE OF NAVIGATION OF THE CHEVALIER <persName>ANTONY PIGAFETTA</persName></title>
    </header>

    <!-- used <term> for astronomy and mapping terms not necessarily used today (R) -->

    <body><p n="1">The armillary sphere, of which the author gives a drawing, serves to explain the
            system of the world according to <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, and could also serve as
            an <term>astrolabe</term>, for one sees at the top of it a kind of handle or ring, by
            which to hold it suspended, as is seen in the above-mentioned drawing. He begins his
            treatise by giving us an idea of that system, as have done all those after him, who have
            written of the elements of the nautical art and of pilotage.</p>
        <p n="2"><q>"The earth is round,"</q> he says, <q>"and remains suspended and immovable in
                the midst of all the celestial bodies. The first index fixed on two poles, the
                arctic and antarctic, which are supposed to correspond with the poles of the earth.
                It runs from <term>East</term> to <term>West</term>, and transports with itself all
                the planets and stars. Besides this there is the eighth sphere, the poles of which
                are at <geo lat="23">23 deg.</geo> 33 min.,<ref n="1">1</ref> it runs from
                    <term>West</term> to <term>East</term>.</q></p>
        <p n="3"><q>"It is supposed that all the circumference of the earth is divided into 360
                degrees; and each degree is of <geo>17 leagues and a half</geo>, consequently the
                circumference of the earth is <geo>6,300 leagues</geo>. Land leagues are of
                    <geo>three miles and sea leagues of four miles</geo>.<ref n="2">2</ref> "The ten
                circles of the armillary sphere, of which the six major pass through the center of
                the earth, serve to determine the situation of countries and climates. The
                    <term>Ecliptic</term> determines the movement of the sun and the planets: the
                two <term>Tropics</term> indicate the point to which the sun declines from the
                    <term>equator</term> towards the <term>North</term> in summer, and towards the
                    <term>South</term> in winter. The <name>Meridian</name>, always variable,
                because it passes through all points of the equator, cutting it perpendicularly,
                designates the <term>longitude</term>, and it is on it that the
                    <term>latitudes</term> are marked."</q></p>
        <subHeading>Of Latitude.</subHeading>
        <p n="4">After having well explained the armillary sphere with all its parts, and their use
            according to the system of <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, the author goes on to teach the
            method of taking the altitude of the pole, on which the <term>latitude</term> is
            calculated; fixing the pole at 0° and the equator at 90°.</p>
        <p n="5"><q>"The Polar star,"</q> he says, <q>"is not precisely on the point corresponding
                to the axis of the earth; but it turns round it, as do all the other stars. In order
                to know its true position with regard to the pole, it must be observed where the
                    <term>Guard stars</term>
                <ref n="3">3</ref> stand. If these are on the western arm, <ref n="4">4</ref> the
                polar star stands one degree above the pole: if they are on the line <ref n="5"/>
                the pole star stands<geo lat="3"> 3 deg.</geo> 30 min. <ref n="6">6</ref> below the
                pole: if they are on the eastern arm the pole star is one degree below the pole.
                When one wishes to take the altitude of the pole star, in whichever of the
                above-mentioned four places the <name>Guard</name> stars may be, the degrees which
                the pole star has above the pole will be subtracted from its altitude, or those
                which it has below the pole will be added to it. I have spoken in the account of the
                voyage of the stars of the <placeName>Antarctic Pole</placeName>.</q></p>
        <p n="6"><q>"The latitude of the place may also be ascertained by the sun's altitude. <lb
                    n="1">1. If you find yourself between the <term>equinoctial</term> and the <placeName>arctic pole</placeName> and
                    the shadow falls towards that pole, look how many degrees and minutes <term>meridianal</term>
                    declination the sun has that day; and this you will subtract from the altitude
                    of the sun which you have taken: afterwards, deducting the remaining degrees
                    from 90 deg., you will have in the residue the number of degrees of North
                    latitude, that is your distance from the <term>equator</term>.</lb>
                <lb n="2">2. If the sun has a <term>boreal</term> declination, in such a manner that the shadow
                    falls towards the south, take the sun's declination on that day, and add it to
                    the sun's altitude which you have taken, from that sum subtract 90 degs., and
                    the remaining degrees will indicate your <term>boreal</term> latitude.</lb>
                <lb n="3">3. If the sun is between the <term>equinoctial</term> and the <placeName>antarctic</placeName>, and the shadow
                    falls towards the <placeName>antarctic</placeName>, observe the sun's declination for that day,
                    subtract it from the altitude taken, according to the first rule, and you will
                    have the degrees of south latitude.</lb>
                <lb n="4">4. If, when you and the sun are between the <term>equinoctial</term> and the <placeName>antarctic
                    pole</placeName>, the shadow falls towards the north, you will add the altitude you have
                    taken to the sun's declination that day, and act according to the second rule. </lb>
                <lb n="5">5. When you have an altitude of 90 deg., you will be so many degrees
                    distant from the <term>equator</term> as there are degrees of the sun's declination, and if
                    the sun has no declination you will be under the <term>equator</term>.</lb>
                <lb n="6">6. If you are to the north of the <term>equator</term>, and the sun is in the southern
                    signs you will look what is its declination, you will add these degrees of
                    declination to those of the altitude observed, and as many degrees as are
                    wanting from 90 deg., so many will you be distant from the <term>equinoctial</term>. </lb>
                <lb n="7">7. You will do the same when you find yourself to the south of the
                    <term>equinoctial</term>, whilst the sun is in the northern signs.</lb></q></p>
        <subHeading>"Of Longitude.</subHeading>
        <p n="7"><q>"Longitude indicates the degrees from east to west: I have considered many
                methods or means for ascertaining it, and I have found three methods <ref n="7">7</ref>
                fitting for that object. The last is the most convenient for those who do not know
                astrology. At the present time the pilots content themselves with knowing the
                latitude; and are so proud that they will not hear speak of longitude.</q></p>
        <p n="8"><lb n="1"><q>"i. From the latitude of the moon the longitude is calculated of the
                    place in which the observation is made. The distance of the moon from the
                    <term>ecliptic</term> is called its latitude: the <term>ecliptic</term> is the path of the sun. The moon,
                    in its movement, always increases its distance until it reaches the furthest
                    point of its distance: and thence it returns back, to diminish, so to say, its
                    latitude, until it is with the head or tail of the dragon <ref n="8">8</ref> there it
                    cuts the <term>ecliptic</term>. And since the moon, whilst it lengthens its distance from the
                    <term>ecliptic</term>, has more degrees towards the west than towards the east, it must
                    necessarily have more latitude on one side (of the globe) than on the other: and
                    when the latitude is known, by measuring the degrees and minutes with the
                    <term>astrolabe</term>, it will be known whether it is found, and how far it is found towards
                    the east or the west. But in order to ascertain the longitude, you must know in
                    what latitude the moon ought to be at that same moment in the place from which
                    you sailed, for instance, in <placeName>Seville</placeName>. By knowing the
                    latitude and longitude of the moon at <placeName>Seville</placeName> in degrees
                    and minutes, and seeing also the latitude and longitude which it has in the
                    place where you are, you will know how many hours and minutes you are distant
                    from <placeName>Seville</placeName>; and afterwards you will calculate the
                    distance in east or west longitude.</q></lb>
            <lb n="2"><q>"ii. The moon furnishes another method for ascertaining the longitude, but
                    that is when I knew the precise hour in which the moon observed at
                        <placeName>Seville</placeName> ought to be in conjunction with a given star
                    or planet, or ought to be in a certain opposition to the sun, of which the
                    degrees are determined: and this I can know by means of an almanack. And since
                    that happens in the east before it happens in the west, as many as may be the
                    hours and minutes that may elapse from the time when the conjunction took place
                    at <placeName>Seville</placeName>, till the time in which I observe it to take
                    place, so much will be my longitude west of <placeName>Seville</placeName>. But
                    if I should see the conjunction take place before the hour in which it ought to
                    happen with respect to <placeName>Seville</placeName>, then my distance in longitude will be east. For
                    each hour, <geo lon="15">fifteen degrees</geo> of longitude are calculated.</q>
                <q>"To understand this does not require any great genius. It should be borne in mind
                    that the moon has a motion opposed to the general motion of the heavens; that
                    is, it goes from west to east, and in every two hours it progresses a degree and
                    a few minutes; and since it is in the first heaven, and the stars are in the
                    eighth, it certainly never enters in conjunction with them; but sometimes it
                    interposes itself before the rays which come from them to our eye: but this does
                    not happen at the same time to those who are at <placeName>Seville</placeName>, and to those who are at
                    <placeName>Valencia</placeName>. The annexed figure will give an idea of this, from which it is seen
                    that the ray of the star d is intercepted by the moon c for those who are at a
                    and not for those who are at b for whom it was intercepted when the moon was at
                    e.</q></lb>
            <lb n="3"><q>"iii. The compass can also supply a method, still easier, for finding the
                    longitude of the place in which you are. It is known that the compass, or the
                    magnetised needle which is in it, directs itself to a given point, because of
                    the tendency which the loadstone has towards the pole. The reason of this
                    tendency is because the loadstone does not find in the heavens any other spot in
                    repose except the pole, and on that account directs itself towards it. This is
                    an explanation of the phenomenon which I propose; and I believe it to be true,
                    so long as experience does not inform us of some better explanation.</q>
                <q>"In order to know, by means of the needle, the degrees of longitude, form a large
                    circle, in which place the compass, and divide it into 360 deg.: and having
                    placed the needle at 360 deg., where it indicates the <placeName>arctic pole</placeName>; when the
                    needle is in repose, draw a thread, which should pass from the <placeName>arctic pole</placeName>,
                    pointed out by the needle to the <placeName>antarctic pole</placeName>, and let this thread be longer
                    than the diameter. After that take the south, which you will know by the
                    greatest altitude of the sun. Turn the compass, until the thread which traverses
                    it coincides with the direction of the <term>meridian shade</term>; then, from the <placeName>antarctic
                    pole</placeName> of the needle, with the thread which remained over, draw another thread to
                    the arctic pole, that is, to the flower; <ref n="9">9</ref> and you will thus find how
                    many degrees the needle of the compass is distant from the <term>meridian line</term>, that
                    is, from the true pole. So many will be the degrees of longitude, which you will
                    have from the place where the compass begins to set itself in motion. <ref
                        n="10">10</ref> Therefore, with the more accuracy you take the true <term>meridian</term> so
                    much the more exactly will you be able to ascertain the degrees of longitude.
                    And from this it may be seen that the <term>meridian</term> should never be taken with the
                    compass, because it north-easts or north-wests, <ref n="11">11</ref> as soon as it goes
                    out of the true <term>meridian</term>; but take an observation of the south <ref n="12">12</ref>
                    with the <term>astrolabe</term>, and judge that it is midday when the sun is at its greatest
                    height.</q>
                <q>"If it is not possible to take the sun's altitude at midday, that can be
                    determined with an hour-glass of sand, taking the hours of the night from sunset
                    till the moment of its rising. Having learned the hours of the night, you will
                    know how many are wanting of the twenty-four, and these you will divide into two
                    equal parts. When half of this has elapsed, be sure that it is midday, and that
                    the shadow indicates to you the true <term>meridian</term>. But since the sand clock may
                    often be inexact, it will be better to take the sun's altitude with the
                    <term>astrolabe</term> by means of its <term>mediclino</term>. <ref n="13">13</ref></q>
                <q>"The true <term>meridian</term> may also be ascertained, or rather the <term>equinoctial line</term>, which
                    cuts the <term>meridian</term> at right angles, by observing the points where the sun rises
                    and sets, and by observing how much they are distant from the <term>equinoctial</term> either
                    to the north or to the south. For this purpose an <term>astrolabe</term> is formed with the
                    globe; that is, a circle is made representing the earth's circumference, divided
                    into 360 deg. At sunrise fix two pins in the circumference, in such a manner
                    that a line drawn from one to the other should pass through the centre, and
                    place the pins so that both should be in a line opposite the sun's center. Place
                    two other pins in the same way in the circumference when the sun sets. You will
                    thus see how much the sun declines from the <term>equinoctial line</term>, either to the
                    north or to the south. And as many degrees as the pins are distant from the
                    <term>equinoctial</term>, so many degrees the the sun's declination. Having found the sun's
                    rising and setting, you will also find the medium distance; that is, the
                    <term>meridian line</term>, and afterwards you will see how much the compass or magnetic
                    needle north-easts or north-wests. You will infer from this how far you are from
                    the <placeName>Fortunate islands</placeName>; that is, from <placeName>Tenerife</placeName> towards the east or the west. This
                    method has been tried by experience.<ref n="14">14</ref></q></lb></p>
        <subHeading>"Direction of the Ship.</subHeading>
        <p n="9"><q>"If you wish to navigate to any place, you must first know its position; that
                is, its latitude and longitude. Then, by means of the compass you will point
                directly to that place. And since the compass varies to east and west, you must, by
                the methods above described, ascertain its variation, and subtract or add that which
                is necessary, so that the ship's head, regulated by the compass, may have the
                required direction.</q></p>
        <p n="10"><q>"Should the compass be lost, or if its variation east or west is not known, you
                may regulate yourself by the sun at midday. When you have fixed the meridian in such
                a manner that it cuts the ship in its width, it will be easy to direct the prow
                wherever you wish. Here is an example: suppose you wish to go from north-east to
                south-west, place the chart in such manner that the ship should have her head to
                west and the poop to the east; then on the circle of the winds, divided into 360, or
                in four times 90, fix two pins, one at 45 degrees between east and north, the other
                at 45 degrees between west and south; bring the two pins on the line of the <term>meridian</term>
                by turning the ship's head for that purpose, and the prow will be directed to the
                place to which you are going. If the pins do not come in a line with the <term>meridian</term>,
                it is a sign that you are navigating in a false direction, and you must rectify the
                course. When you reach land, you will see that what I have said is true.</q></p>
        <p n="11">"With an <term>astrolabe</term> made with plates, <ref n="15">15</ref> observations may be taken of
            the <term>meridian line</term>, the poles, and the <term>equinoctial line</term>, at any hour of the day or night,
            looking at the moon or any star; and for these, place in the middle of the <term>astrolabe</term>
            instead of the <term>verghezita</term> or sight, <ref n="16">16</ref> two straight bars between which you
            will observe the star."</p>
        <p n="12">Thus the method being known by which the required direction is given to the ship,
            the author teaches the method for determining the point or degree on the chart of the
            winds, <ref n="17">17</ref> to which the ship on leaving a place to go to a given country
            should be directed. For clearness, he gives some examples of this. <q>"Do you wish,"</q>
            he says, <q>"to go from south to north, or vice versâ, on the same longitude? always
                proceed on the same <term>meridian</term>. Do you wish to go from east to west, or vice versâ, in
                the same latitude? always proceed on the same parallel. Do you wish to go from one
                place to another as many degrees distant in longitude as it is different in
                latitude? Then take the course of 45 degrees either to the south-west or south-east,
                or north-west or north-east. If the latitude is greater than the longitude, then add
                to the 45 degrees as many degrees towards the nearest pole, as the number of degrees
                by which the latitude exceeds the longitude. For instance, if I wish to go from
                    <placeName>Cape St. Vincent</placeName> to <placeName>Cape Bojador</placeName>,
                I reckon the degrees of longitude and those of latitude to know the difference
                between these two capes. I find that the degrees of <geo lon="5" lat="11">longitude are five and a half,
                and those of latitude are eleven</geo>, from which I subtract the degrees of longitude and
                there remain <geo lat="5">5 deg</geo>. 30 min. Then, instead of going in the direction of from
                north-east to south-west (as I should do if the longitude were equal to the
                latitude], I go from <geo lat="5">5 deg</geo>. 30 min. above north-east towards north, to <geo lon="5">5 deg</geo>. 30
                min. below south-west towards south. If the longitude is greater than the latitude,
                the lesser number is still subtracted from the greater: and the direction will be 45
                <!-- difference values used for explanation in mapping will not be included in geo since they have no relevance to our map -->
                deg. after deducting the residue. For instance, do you want to go from the island of
                    <placeName>Ferro</placeName> to <placeName>Guadeloupe;</placeName> you know that
                the first is in <geo lat="27">27 deg</geo>. latitude and the second in <geo lon="15">15 deg</geo>.; then take their
                difference, which is 12 deg.: look at the map for their longitude, and you see that
                    <placeName>Ferro</placeName> is in 1 deg. and <placeName>Guadeloupe</placeName>
                in 45 deg., whence their difference is 44 deg.: subtract from these the 12 deg.
                residue of latitude, and there remain 32 deg. Then you must subtract these 32 deg.
                from 45 deg., and there will remain 13 deg. Therefore your course will be from
                north-east 13 deg. north to south-west 13 deg. south.</q></p>
        <subHeading>"Direction of the Winds.</subHeading>
        <p n="13"><q>"The rose of the winds, divided into 360 deg., will give a clearer idea of what
                has been here said; it being well understood that the pilot must place the center of
                the winds on the point from which he starts, or from which he takes the course, and
                he must fix the pole to the true pole observed from the sun, and not trusting to the
                compass, which north-easts or north-wests.</q></p>
        <p n="14"><q>"Then, to ascertain whence comes the wind, place a little stick with a little
                sail[18] in the centre of your rose or circle of winds, divided into 360 deg., and
                placed in such a manner that north and south stand on the true <term>Solar
                    meridian</term>. The direction of the vane moved by the wind will indicate
                exactly which wind blows: on the equinoctial is east and west; at 45 deg. there is
                north-east, south-west, north-west, and south-east; at 22½ deg. towards north you
                have north-north-east, and so on with the others."</q></p>
        <references>
            <p><ref n="1">1</ref>Now the declination of the <term>ecliptic</term>, which answers to the poles of the
                    eighth sphere of <persName>Pigafetta</persName>, is <geo lat="23">23 deg</geo>. 28 min. 30 sec.
                    Note, Milan edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="2">2</ref>Supposing that the surface of the globe under the equator were half land
                    and half sea, and then giving to each league three and a half miles, we should
                    have 22,050 miles for the circumference of the earth: a measure very little
                    differing from that which results from giving to each degree at the equator
                    sixty Italian miles, by which the circumference is 21,600 miles. Note, Milan
                    edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="3">3</ref>The guard stars are 6 and 7 of <name>Ursa Minor</name>, which form a
                    triangle with the pole and pole star; now 7 at the belt of
                        <name>Cassiopeia</name> is used. Note, Milan edition.
            </p>
            <p><ref n="4">4</ref>This means the arm of the instrument used; it might be the meteoroscope of
                    <name>Regiomontano</name>, which had a cross in the middle: or an <term>astrolabe</term> like it; or the
                    common astrolabe with a <term>dioptron</term>, or <term>mediclino</term>, as
                        <persName>Pigafetta</persName> calls it, placed on the equator. Note, Milan
                    edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="5">5</ref>That is the<term> meridian line</term> from the pole to the equator. Note, Milan
                    edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="6">6</ref>Though the radius of the circle which the pole star goes round is now
                    little more than a degree and a half, in the time of
                        <persName>Pigafetta</persName> it was <geo lat="3">3 deg</geo>. 17 min. 37 sec, so that if he
                    reckoned it at <geo lat="3">3 deg</geo>. 30 min. it is wonderful that he should have made so small
                    an error, notwithstanding the imperfection of his instruments. Note, Milan
                    edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="7">7</ref>These three methods are probably those which, according to
                        <persName>Castañeda</persName>, <persName>Faleiro</persName> taught to
                        <persName>Magellan</persName>. Note, Milan edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="8">8</ref>That is to say, the knot where the orbit of the moon cuts the <term>ecliptic</term>.
                    Note, Milan edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="9">9</ref>The <term>fleur-de-lys</term> placed at the north.</p>
            <p><ref n="10">10</ref>That is, where it coincides with the<term> meridian</term> and begins to deviate or
                    vary. Note, Milan edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="11">11</ref>That is, varies east or west.</p>
            <p><ref n="12">12</ref>Or of midday.</p>
            <p><ref n="13">13</ref>I do not find any mention of the <term>mediclino</term> in any writer of the times
                    near that of <persName>Pigafetta</persName> who have treated of the <term>astrolabe</term>,
                    such as <persName>Regiomontanus</persName>, <persName>Appianus</persName>,
                        <persName>Gimma</persName>, <persName>Frisius</persName>,
                        <persName>Danti</persName>, <persName>Clavius</persName>, etc.; but from
                    what our author says here and elsewhere, it appears that the <term>mediclino</term> is that
                    movable rule, fixed on the centre of the <term>astrolabe</term>, which turns round it, and is
                    named sometimes <term>albidade</term>, or <term>dioptron</term>, or
                        <term>traguado</term>, or <term>linea di fiducia</term>. Note, Milan
                    edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="14">14</ref><persName>Amoretti</persName>, in his introduction to this Treatise of
                    Navigation, in the Milan edition, observes that <persName>Pigafetta</persName>
                    was misled by a false theory when he supposes that there is in the heavens a
                    point in repose to which the magnetic needle tends, but that the exact direction
                    of the magnetic needle coincided, or at least approximated to the <term>meridian</term> of
                    the <placeName>isle of Ferro</placeName>, which is not now the case; and that in
                    some other places the variation of the compass had been observed to correspond
                    with that of the longitude. By the table of variations of the compass published
                    by <persName>Lambert</persName> in the <placeName>Ephemerides of
                        Berlin</placeName>
                    <name>(Astronomische Jahrbuch)</name> for the year <date when="1779"
                    >1779</date>, it is seen by an easy calculation that at the beginning of the
                    sixteenth century the magnetic equator or zero of deviation was very near the
                    <placeName>isle of Tenerife</placeName>. Now it is further off, and the distance increases. M. de
                    Bouganville found there the deviation to the west to be <geo lat="14">14 deg</geo>. 41 min.; and
                        <persName>Staunton</persName>, the companion of
                        <rank>Lord</rank><persName>Macartney</persName>, found it to be <geo lat="17">17 deg</geo>. 35
                    min.</p>
            <p><ref n="15">15</ref>We have two <term>astrolabes</term> in our museum constructed with several plates: one
                    is of brass, and another of card, for more easy manipulation. Note, Milan
                    edition.</p>
            <p><ref n="16">16</ref><term>"Traguardo,"</term> level or traverser.</p>
            <p><ref n="17">17</ref>"Rosa dei venti."</p>
            <p><ref n="18">18</ref>Or flag, as appears from the drawing.</p>
        </references></body>
</magellan>
